Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Project Records, 1936-1989; 1942-1962; Series IV
  - Jobs 5105, 5205, 5301, 6208: University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI: Campus Planning
    Though office records indicate that Saarinen worked on thirteen projects for the university, including the seven-story brick-and-glass Dexter Housing Development and an adjacent one-story center for continuing education containing an auditorium, only the university's School of Music was erected. Designed in association with Lynn W. Fry, a member of the university's Supervising Architect's Office, an early scheme called for an L-shaped structure and an adjacent, circular concert hall. As completed, the brick-clad concrete School of Music, built into a hill overlooking a pond, consists of a central five-level pavilion housing offices and a library, flanked by wings devoted to performing arts spaces and classrooms. The project team included Severud, Elstad, Krueger Associates, structural engineers; Bolt, Beranek, and Newman, acoustical engineers; and Dan Kiley, landscape architect. After the design of the music school, without hope of completing a coherent scheme for the North Campus, Saarinen resigned as the project's design consultant.
    Job numbers for projects at the University of Michigan overlap and refer to various periods of the project. Many projects that were assigned job numbers are undocumented anywhere in the archives and, as such, are not listed in the finding aid. Jobs 5105, 5205, and 5301 pertain to campus planning. Job 5205 also pertains to the School of Music, and Job 5301 pertains to the Dexter Homestead and Continuation Center. Job 6208 refers to a late addition to the School of Music. The description of the projects below encompasses all of the projects. Saarinen's "Campus Planning" lecture, located in Series II, was delivered to the Board of Regents at the University of Michigan after his resignation from the master planning project.
    - Brochure:k University of Michigan, 1954 (Box 671, Folder 16)
    - Clippings, 1952, 1955, undated (Box 173, Folder 530)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1960 (Box 173, Folder 531)
    - Drawings: Engineering Lab Group; North Campus Development, undated (Box 175)
    - Photographs
      - Ann Arbor: area maps, aerials, site plans, undated (Box 173, Folder 532)
      - Drawings of buildings and site, 1951, undated (Box 173, Folder 533)
      - Master Plan analysis and presentation, undated (Box 173, Folder 534)
      - Negatives, 1953, 1956, undated (Box 173, Folder 535)
      - North Campus
        - Model, undated (Box 173, Folder 536)
        - Site plans, 1956, undated (Box 173, Folder 537)
    - Presentations
      - Planning Studies III, undated (Box 671, Folder 13)
      - Site plan; requirements; ten-year plan, undated (Folder 688A)
    - Slides
      - As-built North Campus buildings, undated (Box 173, Folder 538)
      - Graphics, undated (Box 173, Folder 539)
      - Models, undated (Box 173, Folder 540)
  - Job 5203: Milwaukee County War Memorial, Milwaukee, WI
    Saarinen, Swanson, and Saarinen's original proposal for this complex, to be built by a citizens' group called the Metropolitan Milwaukee Memorial, Inc., on a six-block site downtown, called for three connected buildings surrounding a two-level courtyard. This scheme was unrealized, as the public favored addressing the city's postwar housing shortage instead of building an art center. In 1952, Saarinen was again asked to design a structure for Milwaukee to commemorate the city's war dead, as well as an art gallery and community meeting rooms. The previously proposed downtown site had been rejected, and the completed structure was built into a forty-foot-high bluff in Juneau Park that rose from the shoreline of Lake Michigan to the city's streets above.
    In the courtyard, which contains two freestanding staircases, a reflecting pool is bordered by granite coping inscribed with the names of the war dead. Shortly after the building's completion, a mosaic mural by Edwin Lewandowski depicting in Roman numerals the first and last years of World War II and the Korean War was installed on the upper level of this facade. The cantilevered wings are constructed of lightweight concrete, then a relatively new building material.
    Saarinen worked with a team including Ammann and Whitney, structural engineers; Maynard W. Meyer and Associates, associate architects; Samuel R. Lewis and Associates, consulting engineers; and Richard Klees and Associates, electrical engineers. James McHugh Construction Company served as general contractor.
    - Brochures
      - "Milwaukee County War Memorial" [site plan sketches], 1951 (Box 671, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 173, Folder 541)
    - Clippings, 1947-1968 (Box 173, Folder 542)
    - Correspondence
      - Grantosa School students, 1958 (Box 173, Folder 543)
        - Additional material, part 1 (Box 674, Folder 64)
        - Additional material, part 2 (Box 677, Folder 108)
        - Additional material, part 3 (Box 683A, Folder 149)
      - Publicity and press, 1955-1962 (Box 173, Folder 544)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural drawings (tracings) (Box 176)
      - Electrical, demolition, kitchen, furnishings; color schedule; miscellaneous drawings (Box 177)
      - Site plan, final, undated (Box 683B, Folder 150)
      - Space comparisons with Kleinhans Music Hall and Vivian Beaumont Theater, undated (Box 681, Folder 132)
      - Structural and mechanical drawings (Box 178)
    - Exhibition label text, undated (Box 675, Folder 81)
    - Interiors
      - Correspondence; cost breakdowns; furniture schedules, 1957-1958 (Box 179, Folder 545)
      - Drawings; color schedules, 1957-1958 (Box 179, Folder 546)
      - Materials samples, 1957 (Box 179, Folder 547)
      - Schedules for venetian blinds, movable partitions, picturemolding, exterior colors & materials; specifications for room lettering, miscellaneous cabinet work, 1957 (Box 179, Folder 548)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, aerial site view, 1956 (Box 179, Folder 549)
      - Exteriors, 1955-1963, undated (Box 179, Folder 550)
        - Additional material (Box 671, Folder 15)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 179, Folder 551)
      - Juneau Park: renderings, sketches, plans, models, 1950-1951 (Box 179, Folder 552)
      - Lakefront rendering, 1953 (Box 179, Folder 553)
      - Lewandowski mural, 1959 (Box 179, Folder 554)
      - Models, [1939],1948, [1953], 1954, undated (Box 179, Folder 555)
      - Negatives and transparencies, 1946-1955, undated (Box 179, Folder 556)
      - Page, Dan [photographer] proof sheets, undated (Box 180, Folder 557)
      - Rendering of final scheme, 1954 (Box 180, Folder 558)
      - Sections; plans; sketches; model, 1954-1955 (Box 180, Folder 559)
    - Slides
      - Exterior and details, undated (Box 180, Folder 560)
      - Graphics and construction, undated (Box 180, Folder 561)
    - Specifications
      - Addenda and bulletins [electrical and general construction], 1955-1957 (Box 180, Folder 562)
      - Architectural [part 1 of 2]; general contract; demolition, 1954-1957 (Box 180, Folder 563)
      - Architectural [part 2 of 2], 1954 (Box 180, Folder 564)
      - Elevators, 1954-1955 (Box 180, Folder 565)
      - Food service equipment, 1955 (Box 180, Folder 566)
      - Mechanical; heating and ventilating, 1954-1955 (Box 180, Folder 567)
      - Mosaic installation, 1959 August (Box 180, Folder 568)
      - Plumbing, 1954-1955 (Box 180, Folder 569)
  - Job 5204: Time, Inc.
    - Drawings
      - Program, miscellaneous, undated (Box 181–182)
      - Sketches (Box 183, Folder 570)
    - Space survey proofs, undated (Box 183, Folder 571)
  - Job 5205: University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI: School of Music
    - Brochures: "School of Music, University of Michigan", 1954 Apr; 1956 September (Box 671, Folder 16)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural sepias; structural sepias, undated (Box 184)
      - Exterior rendering, undated (Folder 688B–688C)
      - Mechanical and electrical tracings; plumbing, undated (Box 185)
      - Observations of library wall failure recorded on drawings, undated (Box 186)
      - Plan at upper floor area "A", 1963 (Box 180, Folder 572)
      - Presentation, original; design sketches (Box 186)
    - Photographs
      - Entryway, undated (Box 180, Folder 573)
      - Models, undated (Box 180, Folder 574)
      - Negatives, 1956, undated (Box 180, Folder 575)
    - Presentation: Site plan, 1956 (Box 688D)
  - Job 5206: Drake University, Des Moines, IA: Women's Dormitory: Drawings: Furniture working drawings and sketches, undated (Box 187)
  - Job 5207: Drake University, Des Moines, IA: Bible School and Prayer Chapel
    - Drawings, undated (Box 188)
    - Photographs
      - Exteriors: renderings and photos, undated (Box 189, Folder 576)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 189, Folder 577)
      - Negative, undated (Box 189, Folder 578)
    - Specifications, 1953-1954 (Box 189, Folder 581 - 582)
  - Job 5207, 5515: Drake University, Des Moines, IA: Campus Development: Drawings, undated (Box 190)
  - Job 5208: United States Embassy, Helsinki, Finland
    - Area planning, undated (Box 189, Folder 581)
    - Clipping: "U.S. Architecture Abroad", Architectural Forum (reprint), 1953 (Box 189, Folder 582)
    - Correspondence
      - Manufacturers, 1952-1953 (Box 189, Folder 583)
      - Publicity and press, 1955 (Box 189, Folder 584)
    - Drawings
      - Existing building, undated (Box 191–192)
      - Plans, elevations, undated (Box 193)
      - Sketches and plans, undated (Box 194–195)
    - Photographic negative, undated (Box 189, Folder 585)
  - Job 5209: General Motors Technical Center, Warren, MI: Drawings: Engineering Group miscellaneous details, undated (Box 196)
  - Job 5301: University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI: Dexter Homestead and Continuation Center
    - Drawings, undated (Box 197)
    - Photographs
      - Continuation Center rendering, undated (Box 189, Folder 586)
      - Dexter Homestead: rendering, site plan, existing site condition, 1953, undated (Box 189, Folder 587)
      - Negative, undated (Box 189, Folder 588)
  - Jobs 5302, 5706, 6305: Concordia Senior College, Fort Wayne, IN
    The Lutheran Church–Missouri Synod hired Eero Saarinen and Associates to design a campus for Concordia senior College, which was founded to prepare students for the ministry [Concordia Senior College is now known as Concordia Theological Seminary]. Occupying a 191-acre site on the banks of the St. Joseph River, the college comprised approximately forty structures, masterplanned by Saarinen, with the principal academic buildings bordering a plaza dominated by an A-frame chapel and three ranges of dormitories radiating outward along diagonal axes. All of them incorporate steeply pitched gray-tile roofs with the ridges oriented east-west; long buildings running north-south featured series of gable roofs. In an effort to avoid cutting the bricks where they abut the pitched roofs, Saarinen worked with the project's structural engineers, Severud, Elstad, Krueger Associates, and contractor, A. C. Wermuth, to design and produce diamond-shaped bricks. Saarinen replaced the program's call for three dormitory halls, each accommodating approximately 150 students, with a grouping of thirteen dormitories, each serving 36 students on staggered floors. The dormitories did not exceed the size of the largest houses found in the vicinity.
    From its position on a small ridge that constitutes the site's highest point, the campus chapel overlooks a man-made lake, which had formerly been a meadow. Inside, the chapel is illuminated with natural light through a row of small windows at the base of each sloping wall, a skylight running along the roof ridge, and a vertical glass band on one side of the altar. Hubbard, Lawless, and Blakeley served as the mechanical and electrical engineers; Richard Kelly, lighting designer; and Dan Kiley, landscape architect.
    Job numbers for projects at Concordia Senior College (1954-1965) overlap and refer to various periods of the project. Job 5302 refers to the period of the project during which most of the design and construction was completed; Job 5706 includes the architectural and electrical specifications for the campus, and Job 6305 pertains to additional dormitories and a counselor's house.
    - Architecture and the Church, Commission on Church Architecture of the Lutheran Church - Missouri Synod, 1965 (Box 189, Folder 589)
    - Brochures and progress reports, 1958, undated (Box 189, Folder 590)
    - Clippings, 1954-1963 (Box 189, Folder 591)
      - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1955-1962 (Box 189, Folder 594 - 595)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural, structural, plumbing, electrical, heating tracings
        - Additional Dorms and Counselor's House [Job 6305], undated (Box 198)
        - Auditorium; Administration Building, undated (Box 199)
        - Chapel; Library, undated (Box 200)
        - Classroom Building; Faculty Offices; Health Center, undated (Box 201)
        - Commons; General; Physical Education Building, undated (Box 202)
        - Counselor's House; Men and Women Staff Residences, undated (Box 203)
        - Dormitories; President's House, undated (Box 204)
        - Kitchen, undated (Box 205)
        - Three-Bedroom, Two-Bedroom, and Duplex Houses, undated (Box 206)
      - Bulletins and miscellaneous details, undated (Box 207)
      - Details, sections, elevations, 1955-1956 (Box 189, Folder 594)
      - Elevations, south and west, undated (Folder 689C)
      - Furniture tracing; furniture layouts; color schedules, undated (Box 208)
      - Plans, elevations [photostatic copies], 1955-1958 (Box 677, Folder 109)
      - Site and landscaping working drawings, undated (Box 206)
      - Sketches, [1953] (Box 189, Folder 595)
    - Interiors
      - Interior and exterior color schedules with color samples, 1956-1957 (Box 189, Folder 596)
      - Lounge floor plans with color and fabric samples, 1956 (Box 209, Folder 597)
    - Lutheran art file, 1947, 1955, 1957 (Box 209, Folder 598)
    - Photographs
      - Aerial views, 1956, 1958, undated (Box 209, Folder 599)
        - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 18)
      - Campus views, undated (Box 209, Folder 600)
      - Chapel
        - Exterior views, 1956-1959, undated (Box 209, Folder 601)
        - Interior views, 1958-1959, undated (Box 209, Folder 604 - 605)
      - Construction
        - Administration: building #1, 1955-1956 (Box 209, Folder 604)
        - Auditorium: building #4, 1955-1957 (Box 209, Folder 605)
        - Chapel: building #9, 1956-1957, undated (Box 209, Folder 606)
        - Classrooms: building #2, 1955-1957, undated (Box 209, Folder 607)
        - Commons: building #5, 1955-1957 (Box 209, Folder 608)
        - Counselor's houses 5A, 5B, 5C, 1956-1957 (Box 210, Folder 609)
        - Dining hall: building #6, 1955-1957 (Box 210, Folder 610)
        - Dr. Neeb [?] at site, undated (Box 210, Folder 611)
        - Dormitories #1-#13, 1956-1957 (Box 210, Folder 614 - 625)
        - Faculty houses 2A-2F, 2J-2L, 1956-1957 (Box 210, Folder 626 - 634)
        - Faculty offices: building #3, 1955-1957 (Box 210, Folder 633)
        - Gymnasium, 1956-1957 (Box 211, Folder 634)
        - Health center building: building #7, 1955-1957 (Box 211, Folder 635)
        - Library: building #8, 1955-1957 (Box 211, Folder 636)
        - President's house, 1956-1957 (Box 211, Folder 637)
        - Staff residence 6A: Men's, 1956-1957 (Box 211, Folder 638)
        - Staff residence 6B: Women's, 1956-1957 (Box 211, Folder 639)
      - Doors, 1958, undated (Box 211, Folder 640)
      - Korab, Baltazar proof sheets, undated (Box 211, Folder 641)
      - Miscellaneous rooms, undated (Box 211, Folder 642)
      - Models: early, intermediate, final, 1954, undated (Box 211, Folder 643)
        - Additional material (Box 675, Folder 82)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 211, Folder 644)
      - Publicity binder, 1959 (Box 211, Folder 645)
      - Saarinen, Eero
        - At dedication ceremony, 1958 (Box 211, Folder 646)
        - Displaying model, undated (Box 211, Folder 647)
      - Site plans; sketches; renderings, 1954-1955, undated (Box 211, Folder 648)
    - Program information, 1953-1954, undated (Box 211, Folder 649)
    - Slides
      - Aerial views, 1958, undated (Box 212, Folder 650)
      - Construction and details, 1958, undated (Box 212, Folder 651)
      - Finished exteriors and interiors, undated (Box 212, Folder 652)
      - Graphics and model, 1963, undated (Box 212, Folder 653)
    - Specifications
      - Contract #1: sewers, water mains, roads and grading, 1954 (Box 212, Folder 654)
      - Contract #2: bulletins, 1955-1957 (Box 212, Folder 655)
      - Contract #2: specifications and addenda, 1955 (Box 212, Folder 656)
      - Contract #3: dormitory units 1-6, bulletins, and addenda, 1955 (Box 212, Folder 659 - 660)
      - Contract #5: food service equipment, 1955 (Box 212, Folder 659)
      - Contract #6: faculty housing, bulletins and addenda, 1955-1957 (Box 212, Folder 662 - 663)
      - Contract #7: sound and intercommunication system, 1955 (Box 212, Folder 662)
      - Contract #8: underground water reservoir and pumping station, 1955 (Box 212, Folder 663)
      - Contract #9: physical education building and housing units, 1956 (Box 213, Folder 666 - 667)
      - Contract #10: chapel, bulletins and addenda [missing bulletin #1], 1956-1957 (Box 213, Folder 668 - 669)
      - Contract #11: campus lighting, 1956 (Box 213, Folder 668)
      - Contract #13: site development, 1956 (Box 213, Folder 669)
  - Job 5303: Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA: Chapel
    - Clippings, 1984, undated (Box 213, Folder 670)
    - Drawings
      - Addenda and details, 1954 (Box 213, Folder 671)
      - Architectural tracing; mechanical tracings; electrical; miscellaneous drawings, bulletins, addenda, undated (Box 214)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, 1954 (Box 213, Folder 672)
      - Exteriors, 1962, undated (Box 213, Folder 673)
      - Interiors, 1955-1962, undated (Box 213, Folder 674)
      - Models, undated (Box 213, Folder 675)
      - Plans; sections, 1953 (Box 213, Folder 676)
      - Renderings, 1953, 1959, undated (Box 213, Folder 677)
      - Roszak spire
        - Installation, 1955 (Box 213, Folder 678)
        - Model, undated (Box 213, Folder 679)
    - Specifications, 1954 (Box 215, Folder 680)
  - Job 5305: Miller, J. Irwin Residence, Columbus, IN
    The Saarinen office designed this one-story residence for businessman J. Irwin Miller and his family. It occupies a large suburban site close to a busy street but is screened from it by tall hedges. The eighty-by-one-hundred-foot house is clad in glass and panels of blue-gray slate and white marble, and sits on a paved plinth that extended beyond its exterior walls to form terraces and a parking court. Its rear garden facade runs parallel to an allée of trees, overlooking a hill that led down to a river flood plain approximately 800 feet away. The house is supported by sixteen cruciform steel columns set free from the walls and painted white. The plan was functionally zoned, with one each devoted to spaces for the parents, children, guests, and service facilities. At the center of the house is a ten-foot-high, thirty-by-forty-foot skylit living space, with a distinctive freestanding fireplace suspended from the ceiling and developed in the office by Balthazar Korab; a fifty-foot long storage wall; and a fifty-foot-square sunken conversation pit.
    Kevin Roche was the senior designer on the project. Alexander Girard designed fabrics, carpets, and other furnishings; he also helped Xenia Miller select decorative objects. Dan Kiley created the landscape. Documentation for this project and for the pool house renovation (Job 7001) spans 1958-1984.
    - Clippings
      - "A Contemporary Palladian Villa", Architectural Forum [photocopy], 1958 (Box 215, Folder 681)
      - Miscellaneous, 1959, 1962 (Box 672, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1958-1962 (Box 215, Folder 682)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural, structural, electrical, mechanical, undated (Box 216)
      - Interior plan [colored pencil], undated (Folder 690A)
      - Lighting and painting, undated (Box 217)
      - Marble Institute of America (MIA) blueprint set, undated (Box 218)
      - New sun shield for living room thermostat, 1959 (Box 215, Folder 683)
      - Pool and Bath House and Library [Job 7001], undated (Box 219)
      - Sketches, undated (Box 220)
    - Photographs
      - Exteriors, 1959; undated (Box 215, Folder 684)
      - Fireplace studies, undated (Box 215, Folder 685)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 215, Folder 686)
      - Korab, Baltazar proof sheets, undated (Box 215, Folder 687)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 215, Folder 688)
      - Plans; sections; model, undated (Box 215, Folder 689)
    - Slides
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 215, Folder 690)
      - Interiors, 1958, undated (Box 215, Folder 691)
      - "Pavillion" bath house, 1968, undated (Box 215, Folder 692)
    - Specifications
      - House; bench and paving; re-roofing, 1955-1977 (Box 215, Folder 693)
      - Re-roofing, 1984 (Box 215, Folder 694)
      - Storage building and yard work, 1957 (Box 215, Folder 695)
  - Job 5306: Stephens College, Columbia, MO: Chapel
    In response to a request by this Baptist-sponsored women's junior college for a chapel at the geographic center of its campus, Eero Saarinen and Associates designed a square building with four nearly identical facades. On each side, a blank wall, composed of the same simple brick used throughout the campus, is punctuated by a small vestibule embellished with stained-glass panels designed by the artist Robert Sowers.
    - Clippings, 1957-1959 (Box 215, Folder 696)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1961-1962 (Box 221, Folder 697)
    - Drawings: Architectural, structural, mechanical, electrical, furniture tracings, undated (Box 222)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, 1956 (Box 221, Folder 698)
      - Existing conditions, undated (Box 221, Folder 699)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 221, Folder 700)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 221, Folder 701)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 221, Folder 702)
      - Site plan; section; elevation; floor plan, 1954 (Box 221, Folder 703)
    - Slides: exteriors, undated (Box 221, Folder 704)
    - Specifications, 1955 (Box 221, Folder 705)
  - Job 5355: General Motors Technical Center, Warren, MI: Proposed experimental engineering building: Specifications, 1944 (Box 221, Folder 706)
  - Job 5408: Vassar College, Emma Hartman Noyes House, Poughkeepsie, NY
    The curving footprint of this four-story, 156-student women's dormitory conforms to the circular open area it faced. Saarinen's original design called for two connected buildings that together bordered half of the circle; as built, Noyes House defines only a quarter of it. The building, with structural engineering by Severud, Elstad, Krueger Associates, consists of poured-in-place reinforced roof and floor slabs and precast, tilt-up, load-bearing exterior panels faced in rough-surfaced brick set in black mortar. All rooms contain simply detailed built-in furniture designed by the Saarinen office. Saarinen also studied the Main Hall for possible renovation (Job 5408-A), but there is no evidence in this collection to suggest that he actually completed the job.
    - Campus map with annotations by Saarinen, undated (Box 221, Folder 707)
    - Clippings, 1958-1960 (Box 221, Folder 708)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1959-1962 (Box 221, Folder 709)
    - Drawings